A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, general correspondence, RG 2, 1971-1980 FA401
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, general correspondence, RG 2, 1971-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
FA401
4.94 Cubic Feet 494 35mm microfilm reels.
Biographical/Historical note
Rockefeller Foundation general correspondence:
The existence of a separate General Correspondence file is in part a result of the reorganization in 1927-1928 of the various philanthropic boards founded by the Rockefeller Family. The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial consolidated with the Foundation; some of its programs emerged in the Division of Social Sciences. The humanities interests of the General Education Board were taken over by the Foundation and provided a basis for the Foundation's new Division of Humanities. The International Health Board was reorganized and renamed the International Health Division. Subjects in material previously processed as the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial Collection, the General Education Board Collection and the International Health Board/Division (Rockefeller Foundation Archives, Record Group 5) is thus continued in the General Correspondence -- particularly in the case of the International Health Board.
The Rockefeller Foundation:
The Rockefeller Foundation was established by act of the New York State Legislature approved by the Governor on May 14, 1913, "to promote the well-being of mankind throughout the world." Between 1913 and 1928 the China Medical Board, the International Health Board, and the Division of Medical Education functioned as divisions of the Foundation, concentrating on the administration of programs in public health and medical education. A Division of Studies was created in 1923 to handle projects outside the medical field. These early years were experimental as the new foundation studied the methods of philanthropy and explored its relationships with other Rockefeller boards.
Although the Rockefeller Foundation is the largest and best known philanthropy founded by the Rockefeller family, it was neither the first nor the last to be established. The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (1901), the General Education Board (1902), the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease (1909), and the Bureau of Social Hygiene (1911) all existed earlier. When the Foundation was created, the Sanitary Commission was disbanded. After the establishment of the Foundation, the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial (1918) and the International Education Board (1923) were created.
The Rockefeller boards and their programs were reconsidered and reorganized in 1927-1928 in order to avoid overlapping programs. The International Health Board of the Foundation was disbanded and an International Health Division was organized. The China Medical Board, Inc., was established as a separately incorporated institution, and the China Medical Board of the Foundation ceased to exist. The Division of Studies was dropped and the Division of Medical Education was phased out. The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial was combined with the Foundation and the Spelman Fund of New York was chartered to continue activities of the LSRM that were not absorbed by the Foundation. The International Education Board was disbanded.
As a result of this reorganization, the Foundation adopted a program which included public health work (administered by the IHD), the advancement of knowledge in the medical and natural sciences (in part taken over from the IEB), the social sciences (formerly the field of the LSRM), and the humanities and arts (shared with the GEB). The Rockefeller Institute and the Bureau of Social Hygiene were not affected by the reorganization. The program adopted by the Foundation at this time remained basically the same for the next twenty years.
As its files accumulated, the Foundation maintained a card index recording the names of institutional and individual grantees and correspondents. A microfilm copy of this index is available at the Archive Center.
Scope and Contents note
Rockefeller Foundation general correspondence:
Correspondence of The Rockefeller Foundation consists principally of material not directly connected with an institutional grant. It includes inter-office memoranda, correspondence between field officers and the home office; extracts from officers' diaries; forms and other material relating to fellowships; casual requests for information, employment, or aid; printed matter; and letters of abuse received by the Foundation. As such, the General Correspondence provides insight into the day-to-day workings of the Foundation.
Programs other than public health are not amply represented in the early portion of the General Correspondence. Material on the Division of Humanities and the Division of Social Sciences is especially scanty before 1935. After 1940, the volume of this material increases steadily. Indeed, the General Correspondence files as a whole are relatively compact up to 1940; after 1941, they expand enormously.
Some of the most important features and subjects of these files are as follows:
100: STAFF COMMUNICATIONS AND INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS
This designation applies to two distinct types of documents.
(1) STAFF COMMUNICATIONS. Much of the material under this heading consists of correspondence between or regarding staff officers (eg. a field officer and a member of the home office staff), or gives details of employment and assignment of the field officer. Thus this file is in the nature of a supplement of the Foundation's personnel records. Correspondence between retirees and active staff members is often also filed under this designation, under the names of the individuals. One will also find here inter-office correspondence from the New York headquarters. Of special interest in this connection are the memos of Raymond B. Fosdick (President of the Rockefeller Foundation, 1936-1948), which usually consist of several folders for each year indicated. Some correspondence with trustees, especially Thomas B. Debevoise, may also be found here.
(2) INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS. Correspondence between The Rockefeller Foundation and the League of Nations (especially with Arthur Sweetser) lodges under this heading and persists into the 1940s. After the establishment of the United Nations Organization in 1944/5, documentation of the Foundation's cooperation with various U.N. efforts is to be found. Of special interest are the files regarding Selskar M. Gunn and Warren Weaver's service with UNRRA (1944-1946) and John Marshall's presence as an observer at the earliest organizational meetings of UNESCO (1946-1947).
200: THE UNITED STATES (201-258: Individual States and Territories)
The largest concentration of material is to be found under this designation. It is also the most miscellaneous in character. Correspondence ranges from communications with Federal agencies and departments, to letters of advice, records of interviews, appeals for aid, employment inquiries, and crank mail.
The vast bulk of these files dating between 1927 and 1939 relates to the work of the International Health Division, supplementing material previously processed as RG 5. This includes material on grants to state boards of health, training grants for public health personnel at stations in Ohio or Mississippi, and advice on administrative matters. Following the practice of the IHD, most of these earlier files were arranged under an individual state heading rather than under that of the nation as a whole. By 1935 most of the IHD activities had declined as funding became available to the states through the Federal government for this purpose. Correspondence with the individual state agencies shrank accordingly. The advisory functions of the IHD thereafter took place mainly in the form of pooling information (and occasionally personnel) with the U.S. Public Health Service.
Those states files which remain sizeable after 1935 (such as 216: Illinois-University of Chicago, and 248: Tennessee: TVA) do not relate primarily to IHD activities. In 1951, the use of state numbers in filing was almost totally abandoned.
200: UNITED STATES PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE
During World War II, the Foundation maintained close ties with USPHS, as reflected in the large file of correspondence between Foundation officers and various USPHS officials. This file refers particularly to the Foundation's effort to provide yellow fever vaccine to the Armed Forces. Also of interest for this period is a set of weekly reports on the incidence of virulent disease (plague, smallpox, etc.) around the world.
200E: FELLOWSHIPS
The earlier portion of material so designated (through 1935) is taken up with grants for training public health personnel as requested by various state boards of health. It thus amplifies the documentation of IHD activities noted above. This material includes both declinations as well as acceptances.
Similar material through the 1930s is to be found under 200S: Social Science Research Council, consisting mostly of application forms and correspondence concerning potential SSRC grantees.
For the years 1945-46, an extensive file of Postwar Fellowships follows the regular fellowship file in the General Correspondence. While the character of Foundation support of these Fellows is unclear, the advisory function of Foundation officers in their selection and placement is amply documented here.
300-833: INDIVIDUAL NATIONAL FILES
The files under this heading include administrative and budgetary material for field offices, reports of interviews with potential grantees, governmental and educational figures, diary extracts (usually travel notes, sometimes quite extensive), and miscellaneous correspondence with private and public scientific or cultural institutions and individuals. The majority of this material (especially before 1935) continues the records of the IHD in its international program (see RG 5), and deals primarily with public health programs and medical training. After 1935, the subject matter in the files becomes more diversified.
Scattered throughout these series are observations by Foundation officers on the political and social climate around the world. The Rockefeller Foundation maintained political neutrality regarding the internal affairs of host countries, and cooperated closely with governmental ministries and state-controlled universities -- especially in the areas of public health and the social sciences. Nevertheless, a close watch was kept on developments affecting intellectual freedom and the general climate of cooperation which the Foundation saw as the main prerequisite for performing or sponsoring significant work. This is reflected in the General Correspondence files, where one may find contemporary eyewitness reports and informed outside opinions on such phenomena of this century as the development of Fascism in Europe, the growth of Communism in eastern Europe and China, and the rise or fall of various dictatorships in Latin America.
Large quantities of material may be found under the following headings:
300: South America 315: Cuba 400: Great Britain 427: Canada 437: Jamaica 464: India (including 464.1: Mysore and 464.5: Travancore, through 1944) 500: France 601: China 700: Europe
The bulk of these files indicates either high levels of Foundation activity or the presence of a field office in the country concerned, and thus an "Administration" file will be found here as well as material filed alphabetically or under a program letter. Special features include the 1945-46, 500E file (France-Government Fellowships), which consist of material similar to that described under 200E for the same period. Under 700, one will also find material on the Paris Field Office supplementing that processed separately as RG 6.1.
SPECIAL TOPIC: REFUGEE SCHOLARS, 1933-1946
The General Correspondence contains a mass of material on the plight of European scholars deprived of means or work by the rise of Fascism. This material is similar and supplementary to that found in RG 1 under the same heading. Most of the material in the General Correspondence bearing on this topic may be found as listed below:
717: Germany--Refugee Scholars, 1933-1939 789: Poland-----Refugee Scholars, 1936-1939 200: U.S.---------Refugee Scholars, 1940-1945
These files generally fall into two parts:
(1) A chronological file entitled "Exiled Scholars" which consists of officer's correspondence, diary extracts, lists of exiled academics compiled from various sources, correspondence with various committees and institutions engaged in placing these scholars, and copies of the minutes of those committees with which The Rockefeller Foundation cooperated most closely.
(2) An alphabetical file of correspondence with or concerning individual scholars whose placement the Foundation sponsored or financed in part.
(3) Much material filed under 700: Europe and individual European country numbers (including 400: Great Britain, and 805: Turkey) during the period 1933-1945 also deals with this topic.
Arrangement note
The original filing system has been retained. As with RG 1 (Project Files), this filing system is geographic-numeric; i.e., each country, state, and/or geographic region has been assigned a specific number that is used as the basic document classifier. Letters following a number refer to the project area to which the document refers. An individual or institution is in most instances used as the secondary classifier. This secondary classifier may denote either the institution or the individual from which the correspondence derived, or the subject of the correspondence itself. The principal difference in organization between the RG 1 and RG 2 is that General Correspondence is also organized in annual blocks, while individual project files may cover a number of years.
Important irregularities in the original filing order are noted below:
(1) 100 files are strictly alphabetical until 1941; after 1941, miscellaneous A-Z files are maintained containing small amounts of material on individuals. These immediately follow the main 100 file.
(2) Correspondence with various state boards of public health precede the alphabetical file for each state or territory of the United States (201-258).
(3) Administration files for RF field offices precede the alphabetical file for the country in which they were established.
Post-1951 General Correspondence is processed as annual blocks of material and added to this register when work on the material for each year is completed.
Conditions Governing Access note
Records more than 20 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Archival records have been reformatted to microfilm. User copies are available for research.
Other Finding Aids note
Other available finding aids describing Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence include:
FA308 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1924-1939
FA758 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1940-1946
FA759 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1947-1951
FA425 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1952-1957
FA400 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1958-1970
FA402 Rockefeller Foundation records, General Correspondence, 1981-1990
China; Charities; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Canada; Arts; France; Great Britain; Philanthropy -- United States; Humanities; Fascism -- Europe; Fascism; Europe; Dictatorship -- Latin America; Dictatorship; Cuba; Communism -- Europe, Eastern; Communism; Public health; Jamaica; India; Medical education; Life sciences; Medical sciences; Medical research; Refugee Scholars -- Germany; Refugees; Social sciences; South America; United States; Refugee Scholars -- World War II; Refugee Scholars -- Poland; Philanthropy; Viruses -- Research; Refugee Scholars -- United States; Yellow fever; Yellow fever -- Vaccination; Unesco; United Nations
- General Correspondence, 1971
  Appraisal note
  The archival material has been reformatted and the original records are no longer available. User copies of the microfilm are available for scholarly access.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
  - International, 1971/100
    - Consultant (Nelson, Walter L.) (Reel 1, Frame 1)
    - Consultants (B-M) (Reel 1, Frame 24)
    - Consultants (R-T) (Reel 1, Frame 86)
    - Kemp, Graham E. (Reel 1, Frame 135)
    - Niederhauser, John S. (Reel 1, Frame 283)
    - Rachie, Kenneth O. (Reel 1, Frame 400)
    - Rachie, Kenneth O. (Manuscript) (Reel 1, Frame 469)
    - Staff Members Occasional Papers (C-O) (Reel 1, Frame 881)
    - Staff Members Occasional Papers (S-U) (Reel 1, Frame 1031)
    - Staff Members Occasional Papers (W) (Reel 2, Frame 1)
    - A (Reel 2, Frame 103)
    - B (Reel 2, Frame 186)
    - C (Reel 2, Frame 397)
    - D-F (Reel 2, Frame 677)
    - G (Reel 2, Frame 864)
    - H (Reel 2, Frame 957)
    - I-J (Reel 2, Frame 1134)
    - K-L (Reel 3, Frame 1)
    - Ma-Mc (Reel 3, Frame 160)
    - Mi-My (Reel 3, Frame 412)
    - N-O (Reel 3, Frame 531)
    - P-Q (Reel 3, Frame 809)
    - R (Reel 3, Frame 1045)
    - Sa-Sp (Reel 4, Frame 1)
    - St-V (Reel 4, Frame 214)
    - Wa-Wi (Reel 4, Frame 449)
    - Wo-Y (Reel 4, Frame 741)
  - International Organizations, 1971/103
    - Atlantic Institute (Environment) (Reel 4, Frame 898)
    - Atlantic Institute, Environment (Supplementary Material) (Reel 4, Frame 1037)
    - International Conference on Nutrition (Reel 5, Frame 1)
    - International Conference on Nutrition (Supplementary Material) (Reel 5, Frame 32)
    - International Planned Parenthood Federation (H-M) (Reel 5, Frame 179)
    - International Union for Conservation of Nature and Resources (Reel 5, Frame 327)
    - International Union for Conservation of Nature and Resources (Supplementary Material) (Reel 5, Frame 352)
    - International (A-P) (Reel 5, Frame 499)
    - International (R-Y) (Reel 5, Frame 818)
    - Tundra Biome Program (Reel 5, Frame 995)
    - Tundra Biome Program (Supplementary Material) (Reel 5, Frame 1006)
    - United Nations (B-G) (Reel 6, Frame 1)
    - United Nations (H-W) (Reel 6, Frame 193)
    - United Nations Development Programme (L-S) (Reel 6, Frame 559)
    - United Nations Educational Scientific and Cultural Organization (Education and Economic Planning in Asia) (Reel 6, Frame 723)
    - United Nations Educational Scientific and Cultural Organization, Education and Economic Planning in Asia (Supplementary Material) (Reel 6, Frame 733)
    - United Nations Educational Scientific and Cultural Organization (B-S) (Reel 6, Frame 850)
    - United Nations Research Institute for Social Development (A-P) (Reel 6, Frame 854)
    - B-C (Reel 6, Frame 861)
    - D-I (Reel 6, Frame 980)
    - P-W (Reel 7, Frame 1)
    - International Organizations - Medical Sciences, 1971/103.A
      - World Council of Churches (Christian Medical Commission) (Reel 7, Frame 135)
    - International Organizations - Virus Studies, 1971/103.V
      - United Nations (World Health Organization) (Reel 7, Frame 197)
  - Bellagio Study and Conference Center, 1971/120
    - Greig, W. Smith (Reel 7, Frame 212)
  - United States, 1971/200
    - Agribusiness Council, Inc. (Wolflisberg, Hans J.) (Reel 7, Frame 218)
    - Agricultural Development Council (M-S) (Reel 7, Frame 296)
    - Ab-Ag (Reel 7, Frame 366)
    - American (A-E) (Reel 7, Frame 545)
    - American Film Institute (Reel 7, Frame 666)
    - American (F-P) (Reel 7, Frame 839)
    - American (S-V) (Reel 7, Frame 954)
    - Andean Foundation (Rural Development) (Reel 7, Frame 1061)
    - Al-Ar (Reel 8, Frame 1)
    - As-Au (Reel 8, Frame 71)
    - Ba (Reel 8, Frame 306)
    - Be-Bi (Reel 8, Frame 484)
    - Bl-Bo (Reel 8, Frame 678)
    - Br-Bu (Reel 8, Frame 805)
    - Carnegie (C-H) (Reel 8, Frame 979)
    - Ca (Reel 9, Frame 1)
    - Ce-Cl (Reel 9, Frame 222)
    - Columbia University (A-P) (Reel 9, Frame 468)
    - Coa-Col (Reel 9, Frame 539)
    - Com (Reel 9, Frame 772)
    - Con (Reel 9, Frame 941)
    - Cornell University (A-W) (Reel 10, Frame 1)
    - Coo-Cos (Reel 10, Frame 338)
    - Cou-Cy (Reel 10, Frame 470)
    - Da (Reel 10, Frame 733)
    - De (Reel 10, Frame 945)
    - Duke University (Naylor, Thomas H.) (Reel 10, Frame 1036)
    - Di-Du (Reel 11, Frame 1)
    - Educational Projects, Inc. (Health Manpower) (Reel 11, Frame 179)
    - E (Reel 11, Frame 422)
    - Fa-Fl (Reel 11, Frame 531)
    - Ford Foundation (Africa Program) (Reel 11, Frame 950)
    - Ford Foundation, Africa Program (Supplementary Material) (Reel 11, Frame 970)
    - Ford Foundation (A-B) (Reel 12, Frame 1)
    - Ford Foundation (C-W) (Reel 12, Frame 137)
    - Fort Lewis College (Indian Students) (Reel 12, Frame 286)
    - Fort Lewis College, Indian Students (Supplementary Material) (Reel 12, Frame 291)
    - Fo (Reel 12, Frame 445)
    - Fr-Fu (Reel 12, Frame 616)
    - Gerlach, Luther P. (Reel 12, Frame 767)
    - G (Reel 12, Frame 887)
    - Harvard University (Concord Field Station) (Reel 12, Frame 1086)
    - Harvard University (Environmental Health) (Reel 13, Frame 1)
    - Harvard University, Environmental Health (Supplementary Material) (Reel 13, Frame 78)
    - Harvard University (A-E) (Reel 13, Frame 245)
    - Harvard University, Kennedy School of Government (Environmental Problems) (Reel 13, Frame 277)
    - Harvard University, Kennedy School of Government, Environmental Problems (Supplementary Material) (Reel 13, Frame 311)
    - Harvard University (F-W) (Reel 13, Frame 632)
    - Ha-Hi (Reel 13, Frame 840)
    - Ho-Hy (Reel 13, Frame 1032)
    - Institute (C-S) (Reel 14, Frame 1)
    - International Center, Hawaii (C-P) (Reel 14, Frame 185)
    - International (B-H) (Reel 14, Frame 332)
    - International (I-T) (Reel 14, Frame 486)
    - Im-In (Reel 14, Frame 685)
    - Io-Iv (Reel 14, Frame 871)
    - Johns Hopkins University (B-S) (Reel 15, Frame 1)
    - J (Reel 15, Frame 104)
    - K (Reel 15, Frame 357)
    - Lee, Maryat (Reel 15, Frame 619)
    - La-Li (Reel 15, Frame 731)
    - Lo-Lu (Reel 15, Frame 884)
    - Mac-Mal (Reel 16, Frame 1)
    - Manhattan College (G-W) (Reel 16, Frame 230)
    - Massachusetts Institute of Technology (A-P) (Reel 16, Frame 289)
    - Man-May (Reel 16, Frame 374)
    - Mc-Me (Reel 16, Frame 589)
    - Michigan State University (Wharton, Clifton R., Jr.) (Reel 16, Frame 710)
    - Michigan State University, Wharton, Clifton R., Jr. (Supplementary Material) (Reel 16, Frame 747)
    - Michigan State University (A-Z) (Reel 16, Frame 856)
    - Mi (Reel 16, Frame 951)
    - Mo-My (Reel 16, Frame 1093)
    - National (A) (Reel 17, Frame 1)
    - National (B) (Reel 17, Frame 233)
    - National (C ) (Reel 17, Frame 250)
    - National (E-I) (Reel 17, Frame 416)
    - National (L-O) (Reel 17, Frame 569)
    - National (P-U) (Reel 17, Frame 704)
    - New England River Basins Commission (Long Island Sound Study) (Reel 18, Frame 1)
    - New England River Basins Commission, Long Island Sound Study (Supplementary Material) (Reel 18, Frame 17)
    - New (C-Y) (Reel 18, Frame 236)
    - Newberry Library (History Projects) (Reel 18, Frame 520)
    - Na-Ni (Reel 18, Frame 937)
    - No-Nu (Reel 19, Frame 1)
    - Oak Ridge Associated Universities (Allied Health Manpower Programs) (Reel 19, Frame 261)
    - Oa-Og (Reel 19, Frame 594)
    - Oklahoma State University (Environment) (Reel 19, Frame 769)